<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The liberty of human nature, discuss'd, stated, and limited, in a sermon preached by J. Lambe.</title>
            <author>Lambe, John, 1648 or 9-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32872</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12775235</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12775235</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93755</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48479)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93755)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1036:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The liberty of human nature, discuss'd, stated, and limited, in a sermon preached by J. Lambe.</title>
                  <author>Lambe, John, 1648 or 9-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Free will and determinism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93755:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIBERTY OF <hi>HUMAN NATURE,</hi> Diſcuſs'd, Stated, and Limited, IN A SERMON. PREACHED</p>
            <p>By J. LAMBE M. A. and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in Ordinary to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1684.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93755:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:93755:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93755:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. CHAP. VI. The latter part of the 12th. Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the Power of any. <hi>The whole Verſe runs thus.</hi> All things are lawful for me, but all things are not expedient, All things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Doctrine of Fate, or the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Human Actions deſtroys Religion, Society, Reaſon, or the very Being of Rational Nature. For if Man were a meer Machine, moved and acted by irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible Springs and Weights without himſelf, there could be no ſuch thing as Reaſon or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, Judgment or Diſcretion, Wiſdom or Folly, Virtue or Vice, Rewards or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, which neceſſarily ſuppoſe a Power of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93755:4"/>Election, of judging, chuſing and refuſing. No Action of him that moves againſt his Will is his <hi>own,</hi> and therefore is not ſubject to any <hi>Character</hi> or Imputation. Indeed he cannot with any propriety be ſaid to <hi>act</hi> at all, but to be <hi>acted upon,</hi> or to <hi>ſuffer</hi> the Impreſſions of irreſiſtible cauſes. Nor is the opinion of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> more pernicious in its conſequences, than it is abſurd and impoſſible in it ſelf. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by common Senſe, for we feel a <hi>Vital</hi> Principle within our ſelves, a perfect Liberty of choice, an abſolute Authority over our own Actions; we perceive how readily our Will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to our Underſtanding, and all our Nerves and Inſtruments of Action, in an inſtant obey the Motions of our Will: and we find our Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſuitable to our Powers, in a world of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Contingencies, in the midſt of different Objects, of ſeveral amabilities, for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our Reaſon and Diſcourſe. If this be falſe, it is impoſſible we ſhould be <hi>ſure</hi> that any thing is true; becauſe it is matter of Senſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93755:4"/>we perceive and feel it every moment in every Action of our Lives.</p>
            <p>But it is not in vain to vindicate the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is alſo the Dignity and eſſential Difference of human Nature, whilſt we our ſelves, who cannot but be delighted with this Divine Prerogative in the <hi>Notion</hi> or <hi>Idea,</hi> are yet ſo willing to miſtake, or part with the thing it ſelf; whilſt we who enjoy a perfect freedom in all our capacities of Intellection, Reaſon and Choice, ſhould nevertheleſs, as if we preferr'd Neceſſity, <hi>voluntarily</hi> ſubject our ſelves to Opinions, and irrational Appetites: whilſt we who are apt to aſſert our Liberty with Heat and Zeal where it is not concerned, ſhould patiently decline it in the greateſt and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Inſtances, where it ought to be exerciſed.</p>
            <p>Like the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Chriſtians, whom all the Reaſon in the world, no not the honor of Chriſtianity it ſelf, could diſſwade from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleading one another, before the Heathen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, becauſe, forſooth! the Courts were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93755:5"/>as open to them as to others, and they would not be abridg'd of their Liberty;<note place="inline">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 1.</note> whilſt as St. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerves, theſe very men, that would not ſo much as forbear an indifferent practice, tho but for a ſeaſon, and for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Goſpel, and at the inſtance of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelf, were yet ſo much miſtaken in their Apprehenſions of Liberty, that at the ſame time they were the baſeſt and moſt <hi>conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> ſervile Slaves, to the worſt of <hi>Maſters,</hi> to brutiſh Paſſions and unnatural Deſires.</p>
            <p>And in the words of my Text, he confutes their vain Conceit, diſcovers their Folly, and reproves their Petulance and Inequality by this univerſal undoubted Rule of Wiſdom,<note place="inline">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 12</note> 
               <hi>All things, &amp;c.</hi> The Text then is a Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the falſe and abſurd Reaſonings of the <hi>Corinthian Converts.</hi> And the Caſe was this:</p>
            <p>The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> accuſes them of two very hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Crimes, the one of a litigious Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſhonorable to Religion, and vexatious
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93755:5"/>to one another, v. 7. the other of Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, with thoſe laſcivious practices which generally attend it, v. 9. Now the anſwer of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s Accuſation is briefly this, <hi>viz. All things are lawful for us.</hi> The Courts of Juſtice are open to all, nor does any Law of God forbid the defence of our Property by Suits at Law: and the diſtinction of meats is now aboliſh'd, we are now allowed to eat of all, and as for the wanton conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of ſuch a Liberty, we are taught that they are neceſſary,<note place="inline">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Ham. in Loc.</note> and therefore ought not to be charged upon us as a Crime.</p>
            <p>And theſe indeed were the looſe and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Doctrines of the place, which they imbib'd by Education: for the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were the greateſt Libertines in the World. Who ſhall control us? <hi>All things are lawful for us,</hi> and it is a manly Virtue to uſe our Liberty, were ſome of their received Sayings, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Aphoriſms of Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Wherefore in the Text, St. <hi>Paul</hi> conſiders
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93755:6"/>ſtrictly this their deceitful and pernicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning; and to clear his way, allows the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Propoſition, <hi>All things are lawful for me,</hi> but ſhows the abſurdity of their conſtruction of it, and practice upon it in two particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Suppoſe it be granted that Man is a voluntary Agent, Maſter of himſelf and of all Creatures, yet this Liberty of human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt not be underſtood of a belluine power of doing what we <hi>liſt,</hi> but only of a freedom from the Force and Impulſe of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Cauſes. Our Liberty is indeed our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Glory, yet altogether ſubject to Reaſon and Diſcretion. So that amongſt indifferent things, as going to Law, about which we are ſimply free, if Reaſon, Prudence, or the Honor of the Goſpel incline to the one part, there we are obliged and bound. <hi>All things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for me, but all things are not expedient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> repeats their Argument, <hi>All things are lawful for me,</hi> which in the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93755:6"/>Authors, is the moſt Elegant Form of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and ſhows that they ſo ignorantly miſtake their own Principle, that their Practices upon it are a direct Contradiction to it.</p>
            <p>Your excuſe for Luxury and Contention is your Liberty, but are ye not aſhamed by an appearance of Liberty, to be ſo eaſily tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pann'd and deluded into real Slavery? Are ye ſuch Children to be caught by a word, and decoyed ſo fooliſhly into Nets and Snares? Do ye not know that the Liberty of Man is ſuch an Authority over his Will and Actions, that he may <hi>always be indifferent</hi> to things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different; that it is a power of conſidering every thing in its proper place, and one thing with Reſpect to another; of gratifying every Appetite and Faculty, without the prejudice or deſtruction of any, of believing, loving and deſiring according to the weight and nature of the thing, and the deciſion of right Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But you, becauſe it is ſimply lawful to go to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93755:7"/>Law, will therefore indulge intemperate heats, and ſuffer your ſelves to be ſo overcome of Paſſion, that the ſtrongeſt Reaſons, no not the Credit of Religion it ſelf are ſufficient to divert you; and becauſe no ſorts of meat are forbidden, common or unclean, you will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>inſlave</hi> your ſelves to the Appetites of the Belly. So fooliſh are you, that in thoſe very acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wherein you think you aſſert your Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, you really deſtroy it; you ſacrifice your Reaſon to thoſe Rebellious Tyrannous Deſires which, of right, are <hi>ſubject,</hi> and might have been kept in due Obedience. <hi>All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any.</hi> As if he had ſaid, If you would preſerve your Liberty, you muſt preſerve the Authority of your Underſtanding; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſubmit your Opinions, Appetites, and Actions thereunto. Since you are endowed with ſuch a Principle, you muſt reſolve that all things ſhall be indifferent to you, till they have paſſed the ſcrutiny of your Judgment,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93755:7"/>that your Will and Affections, ſhall always wait the Reſolution of your Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you a ſhort Account of the occaſion of the Words, it is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to inſiſt any farther upon their particular reſpect and application to the Caſe of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> but I ſhall conſider them, indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Text, as a noble Reſolution of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or as an univerſal Rule of Wiſdom to all Men, in the Government of their Lives, <hi>I will not be brought, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Terms of the Problem are eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and require but little Explication. <hi>I have a power in all things,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of Judging, Chuſing and Acting according to right Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Propoſitions of Truth, Objects of Deſire, and Methods of Practice are infinite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, and about theſe the Reaſon and Judgment of Man is exerciſed; and he has ſuch an abſolute power over his own Opinion and Practice, that he is not determined by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93755:8"/>Fate, Neceſſity, or irreſiſtible Cauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelf, but by certain innate Principles, rational Powers, and the Divine Aſſiſtance, he is enabled to judge of Truth and Goodneſs, and only ſo far obliged to chuſe and act as ſhall appear conductive to his Happineſs, or agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his Reaſon.</p>
            <p>And having thus explained the Principle, the Senſe of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Reſolution or practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Comment thereupon is evident, <hi>I will not be brought under the power of any thing;</hi> I will ſo uſe this Liberty of Judging and Chuſing for my ſelf, that my Opinion, Will and Actions ſhall always remain, as they naturally are, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of my Underſtanding. I will not be deluded by falſe Appearances to believe Abſurdities, to love what is hateful or do what is evil. The words being thus explained may be reſolved into this eaſy Propoſition, <hi>viz. That to preſerve the Authority of our Reaſon and the Liberty of our Will, from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations of Prejudice, ſenſual Appetites and Paſſions, is the Wiſdom and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93755:8"/>of a Man. I will not be brought under the power of any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text may ſeem at the firſt view to countenance Republican Principles and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, but we ſhall find, upon a more exact inſpection, that it was never deſign'd by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> to ſerve the Intereſt of Faction or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to diſſolve or looſen Government, or ſubject the Laws of Princes to the Reaſon and Judgment of the People. This is ſo perverſe, ſo malicious an Explication of the Words, that thoſe who make it, cannot themſelves believe it, becauſe it is ſo direct a Contradiction to thoſe poſitive Declarations and expreſs Precepts of exacteſt Loyalty, which we find in St. <hi>Pauls Epiſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I humbly hope <hi>ill ſounding Words</hi> will not offend, when the deſign of uſing them, is to direct them to their proper places, to right Objects, and deliver them from thoſe groſs A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes which have been ſuper-induc'd upon them.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93755:9"/>
            <p>It is true, for fear of Miſconſtruction, I might have excepted the Laws of God and our Country as <hi>Sacred Things,</hi> about which, generally ſpeaking, we have no Deliberation, Liberty or Election, and therefore fall not under the Conſideration of the Propoſition, or the Rule of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> which only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſuch things as are <hi>wholly</hi> in our Power. And yet there would ſtill have been ſufficient Scope for the exerciſe of our Reaſon, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and Choice.</p>
            <p>For the Laws of Princes chiefly Reſpect the Publick Intereſt, or the Government of the external Actions of Men, as they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Commonwealth: but all Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>indifferent</hi> Nature, all ingenious Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, Philoſophy, Wiſdom, Moral Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, inward Affections, together with almoſt the whole Oeconomy of Private Life, are left to the diſcretion of every man.</p>
            <p>And moſt of the Laws of God are <hi>general,</hi> only the great Lines and Heads of Duties,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93755:9"/>but the application of Particulars, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of one thing to another, the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Affections, and Circumſtances of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are left to the deciſion of Human Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>This I might have done, but it is wholly needleſs to make ſuch Limitation or Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the Propoſition is univerſally true, <hi>viz. That to preſerve the Authority of our Reaſon, and the Liberty of our Will, from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations of Prejudice, ſenſual Appetites and Paſſions, is the Wiſdom and Felicity of a Man.</hi> Indeed, one of the very <hi>firſt,</hi> and moſt obvious Principles of Right Reaſon is, the moſt intire Reſignation of our ſelves to be govern'd by the Laws of God and our Country. And no Man that does not baſely deſert his Reaſon, and <hi>depart</hi> from this incomparable Rule of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> can ever wilfully Sin againſt God, or Rebel againſt his Prince.</p>
            <p>This premiſed, I ſhall now proceed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the truth of the Propoſition with Reſpect
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93755:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>to things <hi>Intellectual, Moral, Civil</hi> and <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,</hi> and ſhow that in all theſe (which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend whatſoever the Judgment of Man is converſant about) <hi>to preſerve the Authority of our Reaſon, and the Liberty of our Will, from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation of Prejudice, and the Briberies of Intereſt, ſenſual Appetites and Paſſions, is the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Felicity of a Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, <hi>With Reſpect to things intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, or in the Study of uſeful Knowledge, and the Government of our Opinon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every perfect Man is born with inherent Topicks of right Reaſon, with a ſufficient Syſtem of natural Logick; his Mind is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd with Standing Principles, and eternal Verities to direct him in the ſearch of Truth, and furniſhed with rational Powers of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one thing with another, of judging Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects by Cauſes, and drawing innumerable and certain Inferences from thoſe undoubted Premiſes.</p>
            <p>This then is the Liberty and Glory of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93755:10"/>Nature, that it is indifferent and free to every <hi>doubtful Opinion</hi> and <hi>diſputable</hi> Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that thoſe who have ſufficient opportunity of improving their Faculties, are enabled to judge for themſelves, and not obliged to aſſent without ſufficient Reaſon; that there is no <hi>force</hi> upon their Minds from within or without them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but as the ſenſitive Faculties do freely judge of Sweet and Bitter, or the qualities of their proper Objects by the Teſt of <hi>Senſe,</hi> ſo the Rational conclude of <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Falſe,</hi> of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> by ſuch demonſtrations as the Nature of the thing requires.</p>
            <p>It is therefore the higheſt point of Wiſdom in the world, to defend this Liberty of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, this Jewel of ineſtimable Value, from the Uſurpations of Prejudice and Paſſion to ſuſpend our Aſſent till we ſhall be ſufficiently convinced; to ſearch for Truth impartially, to purſue it greedily, to love it for it ſelf, and embrace it readily whereſoever we find it: So ſhall we preſerve the Beauty of our Nature,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93755:11"/>and the perfection of our Being. So ſhall we diſcharge our Truſt, and preſerve that Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in our little world which God has inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us withal.</p>
            <p>Not like the Sceptic who reſolves to ſuſpend his Judgment, and remain <hi>indifferent</hi> howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>clear</hi> and full the Evidence may be; this is to prevent the diſeaſes of the Eyes by pulling them out. It is true, he cannot be deceived or impoſed upon by <hi>particular</hi> Propoſitions, but the thing it ſelf, or the reſolution of believing nothing, is the greateſt Deluſion and <hi>Impoſition</hi> of the Mind that can be; for the Mind is greedy of Knowledge, our Faculties are diſpoſed to ſeek it, and the Divine Nature, and all the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances in the world are intended for our Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; and Soul enjoys a Truth with the greateſt delight imaginable: ſo that whilſt the Sceptic pretends to <hi>ſecure,</hi> he really <hi>deſtroys</hi> the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his Mind, he debars it by violence and force from the kind enjoyment of its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Objects.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93755:11"/>
            <p>But Firm, Well-grounded, Rational Aſſent proceeding from a cautious ſearch, from an impartial preparation to believe upon ſufficient Evidence, upon univerſal Principles, regular Deductions, and credible Teſtimony, is the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>proper</hi> Liberty of human Nature, the higheſt Command and Authority over ones ſelf.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Men who alone are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed for the Study of Knowledge, who ſee with their own Eyes, underſtand by their own Judgment, diſcover Truth, improve Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and are highly uſeful in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>But the Sceptick is ignorant and uſeleſs. And a Man, on the other hand, of a <hi>paſſive</hi> Spirit, fond of every Opinion, tenacious of his firſt Impreſſions, of antient Errors, of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Opinions: judging by Intereſt, Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, Affection, Senſe, or any thing but <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reaſon,</hi> is a very ſlave to innumerable, inconſtant, giddy Maſters; to every hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93755:12"/>deſigning Countenance, to every conceited Emperick, bold Aſſertor, falſe Hiſtorian, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Proverb, and to all who by <hi>cunning Arts and Devices go about to deceive.</hi> Oh ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ad ſervitutem nati! <hi>as</hi> Seneca <hi>ſpeaks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the like occaſion, Oh Men! deſtin'd, cut out for Slaves, how monſtrous is it that you ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have all things free, your Bodies, your Goods, your Members, and not your Spirit, which yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is born to Liberty?</hi> It is therefore a wiſe and happy Rule, <hi>I will not be brought under the Power of any thing in Speculation or the ſearch of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as in Speculation, ſo ſecondly <hi>in the Government of our Life and Actions, to preſerve the Authority of our Reaſon and the Liberty of our Will, from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations of Prejudice, ſenſual Appetites and Paſſions, is the Wiſdom and Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of a Man: I will not be brought under the power of any thing in Matters Moral.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The juſt and true deſign of Speculation or the ſtudy of Truth and Falſhood is, that we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93755:12"/>may the better be enabled to judge of Good and Evil. For the ultimate End or higheſt Perfection of Man is a ſteddy, conſtant courſe of laudable Actions, ſuch a rational pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure as ſhall Improve our Faculties, advance our Intereſt and ſatisfie the <hi>true</hi> Diſpoſitions and Inclinations of our Nature. To this are all the Faculties of the Soul intended to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and into this they finally reſolve; we diſcourſe, compare, judge and determine for this end that we may <hi>act</hi> according to right Reaſon.</p>
            <p>All the Kinds of Being in the world, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting Man, are <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>intire.</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels <hi>now,</hi> are Pure and Perfect in their Will and Appetites, immoveably determined to that which is good, they act <hi>freely</hi> and from a <hi>vital Principle,</hi> but yet their Knowledge is ſo diſtinct and clear, that it is ſuppoſed impoſſible they ſhould direct their choice amiſs: Beaſts are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſenſual, moved by certain inſtincts, and impreſſions, which direct them to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93755:13"/>ſatisfactions of their ſeveral deſires. But the nature of Man is <hi>mixt,</hi> he partakes of the Perfections, Quality and Inclinations of all other Kinds of Being whatſoever. He is ſo far Divine and Spiritual, as he moves and acts from himſelf freely, and for the ſake of ends, and is endowed with Principles of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Wiſdom, Knowledge and Reflection. And ſo far alſo ſenſitive and animal, as his Mind is lodg'd in an earthly Body, endowed with Organs of the <hi>quickeſt Senſe,</hi> and ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a world that is furniſhed with all the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions of the animal Life.</p>
            <p>And tho this condition, neither purely ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, nor purely animal be imperfect, yet it is the moſt honourable that can be on earth; it is the nobleſt nature that could be framed with an earthly body. For tho the inferior Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the ſenſitive Appetites are very quick, and the ſame in us as Brutes; yet every Man is <hi>Maſter of himſelf,</hi> capable of underſtanding his <hi>whole</hi> Capacity, of preſerving the Beauty,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93755:13"/>Harmony and Order of his frame; of watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the motions of his Will and Affections: of ſubduing the Predominancy of irregular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and directing them to their proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: finally, <hi>by the Grace of God,</hi> of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving his peculiar Form Intire and Perfect.</p>
            <p>This is that Liberty, that Authority of Man over his Deſires and Actions. His pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince indeed is very difficult, <hi>viz.</hi> to improve and ſatisfie the ſeveral and <hi>contrary</hi> Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his nature to keep his Paſſions equal, and his ſenſitive Appetites in their proper infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior place and order: to prevent Diſeaſes and Sickneſs, Jars and Claſhing, in ſo fine and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a Compoſition, but his natural Power, <hi>aſſiſted by the Grace of God,</hi> is every way pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable. He is able to judge, by inward Impreſſions, by his natural Neceſſities, and by the Divine Revelation, what is fit and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to do or to forbear, and to act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>It is not therefore a brutiſh Licentiouſneſs or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93755:14"/>Liberty of doing what we <hi>pleaſe,</hi> of gratifying the <hi>preſent</hi> Appetite, of proceeding without the conſideration of the effects and conſequence of Actions: ſuck a Liberty is utterly incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, indeed a contradiction to rational Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For the eſſential difference of Man is Conſciouſneſs, or the Knowledge of himſelf with a power of directing his Actions according to Reaſon, that is, with reſpect to his real In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, eſtimated and meaſured by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities of his Nature. That therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be challenged as a Right, or deſired as a Priviledge which directly <hi>deſtroys</hi> our very <hi>Species.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even God himſelf, who certainly enjoys the moſt perfect Freedom as well as all other Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, has yet no Liberty to <hi>Evil.</hi> There is a rule or manner of operation implyed in the Divine Nature; all his Attributes are exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with reſpect and ſafety to each other; there is an Agreement or Harmony in the Divine Perfections which is juſtly ſtyled the Eternal
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93755:14"/>Immutable Law of God. Thus alſo the Liberty of Man in the management of <hi>his</hi> Life, is not a Liberty of living <hi>looſly,</hi> without all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, Bounds and Laws: but of Chuſing, Loving and Acting with relation to his <hi>Real</hi> Intereſt, to the true Diſpoſitions, Inclinations and Capacities of his Nature. And Actions thus proceeding are the only <hi>genuine, free</hi> and <hi>eaſy</hi> Actions of our Lives.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding theſe ſeeming Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, this is the moſt honorable, the moſt <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> ſtate of Ingenuity and Liberty that can be imagined. For it is the liberty of God himſelf. It is this that gives us the Denomination of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Agents. It is this that enables us to live a happy Life, to improve, indulge and gratify, as, well our ſenſitive as intellectual Powers. For he only who is <hi>looſe</hi> from ſenſual Pleaſures <hi>truly</hi> enjoys them. For as <hi>Seneca</hi> well obſerves, <hi>they that are under the power of bodily Pleaſures, cannot be ſaid to have pleaſure, but pleaſure has them, we cannot be ſaid to poſſeſs enjoy what is not under our Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93755:15"/>
            <p>This then is the Glory, the nobleſt Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of Human Nature; and therefore to <hi>preſerve the Authority of our Reaſon, from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations of ſenſual Appetites and Paſſion, muſt ſurely be the Wiſdom and Felicity of a Man. For where</hi> the Will is directed by due conſideration, by a well weighed Judgment, there is Health, Eaſe and Satisfaction. Our Lives will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to God, our Knowledge will be clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more copious, our Appetites indifferent and obſequious, our Affections equal, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd to the value of the Object, our Paſſions calm and regular. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſays of ſuch a Man that he is <hi>Immoveable as God, compell'd of nothing, attempting nothing in vain, never diſappointed, always ſafe, unhurt and free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is this that is true Nobility, true Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Soul, and Greatneſs of Mind; theſe are the moſt perfect of Men, and therefore the moſt beautiful and honor'd in the ſight of all: their Minds are free, their Faculties improved, their Judgment ready, apt for Council, Truſt, Managery, without Hypocriſy, Deſign or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93755:15"/>Intereſt. And thoſe things which flow from a Mans ſelf are his real Honor.</p>
            <p>But as for thoſe who break the Order of this inward Government, who chuſe and purſue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the firſt appearance, and love with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deliberation; who by reaſon of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Converſation with ſenſual Objects, look no farther, but underſtand, eſteem Judge and love with Reſpect to theſe alone; they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a force and coaction of Soul: their natural power over their Deſires and Actions to direct them according to Reaſon and Intereſt, is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped upon by thoſe rebellious Paſſions which of right are <hi>ſubject</hi> and ought to wait the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of deliberate Judgment.</p>
            <p>And when once this Order is broken, what tumult, what conteſt muſt it neceſſarily raiſe in the Minds of Men? How inſatiable are inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Deſires, how inconſiſtent, and yet how importunate to be gratified? Whilſt Ambition prompts to that which Envy diſallows, Pride commands what Covetouſneſs forbids.</p>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rget enim mentem Dominus non lenis, &amp; acres Subjectat laſſo ſtimulos.</q>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93755:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Or as St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>They are holden pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners of Satan at his Will,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 26.</p>
            <p>And as in Speculation, and in the general inſtitution of Life: So thirdly, in the particular management of ones ſelf, as a Member of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. <hi>To preſerve the Authority of our Reaſon, from the impoſitions of falſe Opinion, Prejudice and Paſſion, is the Wiſdom and Felicity of a Man. I will not be brought under the power of of any thing in matters Civil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Authority of Princes cannot be more highly aſſerted, nor the Obedience of Subjects more ſtrictly enjoyned by than St. <hi>Paul</hi> in many paſſages of his <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> And yet in my Text the ſame St <hi>Paul</hi> may ſeem a great Bigot of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> and upon the queſtion peremptorily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, that <hi>He would not be brought under the power of any,</hi> the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and may be interpreted of <hi>Perſons</hi> as well as things.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſince a contradiction in the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is abhorrent to conceive, we may, be ſure there is a fair Accommodation, and <hi>intire Obedience</hi> according to the firm injunction of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93755:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>may be reconciled and proper <hi>Liberty</hi> of a man with the juſt, aſſerted in the Text.</p>
            <p>And indeed, as hath been already noted, and cannot be too well conſidered, the Liberty of Man in any matter whatſoever, is not an exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant power of acting as he pleaſes, but of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is moſt rational in its nature and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to his happineſs. And this very notion of Liberty were it throughly imbibed, would be a ſufficient Antidote againſt the Deluſions of Hypocrites and the Impoſitions of the Seditious.</p>
            <p>Government is the defence and ſafety of the weak, the foundation of Property the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Civility, Arts, Learning and Religion. Without this the Human Nature would be the moſt ſavage in the world; Reaſon would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into Craft and Malice, and be but an addition of Strength to vex, moleſt and prey upon one another. Wherefore one of the firſt and most obvious reſolutions of Reaſon, is, that we are <hi>subject naturally</hi> and of <hi>right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And amongſt the many Kingdoms and Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties of the world, common Senſe will teach us
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93755:17"/>to account our ſelves the undoubted Subjects of that particular Polity in which we are <hi>Born,</hi> and under whoſe Protection and Influence we live.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the very <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Eſſence</hi> as well as the <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> of any <hi>Government,</hi> is <hi>final determination or abſolute Authority,</hi> therefore Reaſon peremptorily commands the moſt cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Obſervation of whatſoever Laws concerning any matters that are not plainly determined by the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to whom we are primarily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged. Wherefore then, the moſt patient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of our ſelves, our <hi>private Will</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> to the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> we live under, is therefore our <hi>trueſt Liberty</hi> becauſe it is the evident <hi>Reſolution</hi> of <hi>Right Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For any <hi>Government</hi> by how much the more intire, poſitive and abſolute it is, by ſo much the better it is enabled to <hi>ſupport</hi> it ſelf. It is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for <hi>defence,</hi> ſecret in <hi>Councils,</hi> in deliberation <hi>Wiſe and Bold,</hi> without <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> or <hi>Fear,</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution <hi>Potent,</hi> where the <hi>Intereſt</hi> is but one, the ſubjects will be as eaſy as they are ſecure, and the Neighbors juſt and awful.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:93755:17"/>
            <p>But all <hi>Reſervations</hi> of <hi>poſitive</hi> or <hi>real Power</hi> in the <hi>People,</hi> all Exemptions in the <hi>Modes</hi> or <hi>external Celebrations</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> or in any other indifferent matter, from the <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> are pernicious to Societies; they nouriſh a continual <hi>Ferment,</hi> ſupport and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue divers <hi>Intereſts,</hi> ingender <hi>Emulation, Stirs, Heats, Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> intoxicate the common <hi>People,</hi> and fill their Minds with <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, Conceit</hi> and <hi>Pride;</hi> furniſh <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Faction</hi> and <hi>Diſcontent</hi> with plauſible diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes and colors for their <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Iniquity.</hi> In a word, they clog and prejudice the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but it is impoſſible in the nature of the thing, that they ſhould <hi>ſecure</hi> or <hi>ſerve</hi> the <hi>Real Intereſt</hi> of any people in the world.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Authority</hi> of the people is indeed a meer <hi>Chymera,</hi> a word of <hi>Art</hi> to conciliate poor deluded Slaves to the oppreſſions, and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the <hi>Senate,</hi> and in <hi>Fact</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> the Subjects of Commonwealths are as ſeverely governed as thoſe of any Monarchy we know. Wherefore then, the <hi>true Liberty of Man in his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93755:18"/>politic Capacity,</hi> as in all things elſe, is to act as <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that is, the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of human Nature, or the neceſſities of <hi>Society</hi> require, namely with the moſt obſequious <hi>Submiſſion:</hi> To lay aſide the airy Dream of <hi>original imaginary Power</hi> in <hi>him</hi> (that curſed Spring of Miſchief and Confuſion!) to conſider his <hi>Incompetency,</hi> to judge his <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors,</hi> or their proceedings, to be always apt to believe the beſt, and ready to aſſert the <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> (which is the Cement) of the eſtabliſht <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> with <hi>Vigor</hi> and hearty <hi>Zeal,</hi> in his place and ſtation.</p>
            <p>And this is a <hi>Notion</hi> as eaſy to be underſtood as it is <hi>juſt, ſecure</hi> and <hi>ſafe</hi> in practice. But to take the Liberty of the Subject for any <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, Direct</hi> or <hi>Poſitive Authority</hi> reſiding in them is fooliſh to <hi>Abſurdity,</hi> becauſe it deſtroys the very Reaſon, or Principle upon which the <hi>Opinion</hi> it ſelf is founded, namely, <hi>the ſafety of the People.</hi> For if we could ſuppoſe, what can never be made to appear by any Example, a people perfectly free, and at their own diſpoſe that which never was by general content, did
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93755:18"/>appoint and conſtitute a <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Governors,</hi> enduing him or them with ſuch degrees of <hi>Power</hi> as they thought fit, reſerving to themſelves the Sovereignty; ſuch a Government, I ſay, would prove in a little time, impracticable and vain.</p>
            <p>For where <hi>all</hi> have Authority, <hi>none</hi> have. Through corruption of human Nature, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of Men <hi>hate</hi> their Superiors; had they therefore any ſhare in the Government; or any <hi>real power,</hi> it would beget ſuch an haughty opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of themſelves, raiſe ſuch extravagant Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as muſt neceſſarily put the Government into frequent danger of Diſſolution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is therefore the Wiſdom and Felicity of a man, to preſerve the Authority of his Reaſon, from the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of popular opinions, prejudice and paſſion in theſe things.</hi> To conſider his <hi>Station,</hi> and never ſuffer the plauſible <hi>Pretences</hi> of deſigning <hi>Malecontents</hi> to debauch his <hi>reaſon,</hi> or ſhock his <hi>Loyalty:</hi> ſo ſhall he contribute to the preſervation of the <hi>Government,</hi> and in that to his own happineſs, to the free enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the liberty of his <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>will</hi> in all thoſe other things wherein it may be juſtly exerciſed.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:93755:19"/>
            <p>How agreeable would this <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> under the <hi>People</hi> to their <hi>Prince</hi> and to <hi>one another?</hi> what a <hi>Confidence</hi> would it raiſe? what <hi>delight,</hi> what free and cheerful <hi>Intercourſe?</hi> how would all <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſy, Fears, Jealouſies</hi> and odious <hi>Characters</hi> be baniſht human Converſation?</p>
            <p>And it is this, this <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Modesty</hi> in the Subject, that is the beſt ſecurity in the world of <hi>real Priviledges,</hi> of <hi>public Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>ſteddy Government.</hi> There is in Man ſuch a natural <hi>Condeſcenſion,</hi> ſuch <hi>Civility,</hi> ſuch ſenſe of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> obſerved, that it is an affront to the Ingenuity of <hi>Human Nature</hi> to ſuppoſe a <hi>Prince</hi> ſhould be <hi>ſevere</hi> upon a <hi>willing</hi> and <hi>obedient people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thoſe who miſtake the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for ſovereign <hi>Power,</hi> as the <hi>Republican,</hi> or for a freedom from all <hi>Coertion, Laws</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as the <hi>Enthuſiaſt,</hi> or for a Liberty of capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Cenſure, of controlling <hi>Princes,</hi> of reducing them to <hi>Reaſon by</hi> force, of improving and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing upon <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Poſſibilities,</hi> as the <hi>factious Monarchiſt,</hi> theſe, I ſay, whilſt they would ſeem ſo great Aſſerters of their <hi>Liberty,</hi> are, in truth,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93755:19"/>as very Slaves as any in the world. They are always buſied with mighty <hi>Earneſtneſs,</hi> about ſuch matters as are above their <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> but there cannot be a greater miſery than hot and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery <hi>Spirits</hi> acting upon <hi>falſe Appearances,</hi> upon crude and indiſtinct <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſions</hi> of things. How is ſuch a perſon galled and agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated from himſelf, from the confuſion of his <hi>own Mind?</hi> and how fitly is <hi>he</hi> prepared for every <hi>cunning Patriot</hi> and <hi>deſigning Malecontent</hi> to <hi>act</hi> upon? They are bewitched with the <hi>word Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> as with a <hi>Charm,</hi> live in <hi>perpetual paſſion,</hi> in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and imprudent <hi>Zeal,</hi> they govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by <hi>inconſtant Principles,</hi> are diſtracted by multiplicity of new <hi>Deſigns,</hi> neglect their <hi>Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> deſtroy their <hi>Virtue,</hi> expoſe their <hi>Fortunes,</hi> and centre often in an <hi>ignominious Death.</hi> And thus the <hi>Propoſition</hi> is undoubtedly true in our Relation to the <hi>Government: that to preſerve, &amp;c. I will not be brought under the power of any thing in Matters Civil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The time will not permit me to illuſtrate the <hi>Apoſtles Rule</hi> as I propoſed in the laſt place,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93755:20"/>with <hi>Relation</hi> to <hi>Religion,</hi> or in Matters <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Spiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I intended to ſhow that <hi>Man</hi> by <hi>natural inſtinct</hi> found himſelf oblig'd to <hi>worſhip God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he is endued with ſufficient <hi>Abilities</hi> if he carefully employ them, and have opportunity of improving them, to judge of ſuch a <hi>demeanor</hi> or <hi>habit</hi> of life, as is likely to be accepted of him.</p>
            <p>That every man whoſe <hi>Education</hi> and <hi>Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities</hi> will permit him, is obliged to <hi>aſſert</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi> this <hi>Liberty of proving all things, that at length, when he has found the beſt, he may hold it faſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. of determining his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> according as his <hi>Reaſon,</hi> after the moſt <hi>diligent ſearch</hi> and <hi>faithful uſe</hi> of all the means of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> ſhall direct him</p>
            <p>That <hi>Reaſon</hi> will prompt him, to conſult the <hi>Law of Nature, the common Senſe of man-kind, the divine Revelation, the conſent of the univerſal Church, the Authority of the Church he lives in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That whoſoever judges of <hi>true Religion</hi> by theſe rules, (which are the <hi>Principles in the ſtudy of Religion,</hi> wherein alone the Mind can
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93755:20"/>reſt, and ſatisfie it ſelf) <hi>acts</hi> moſt rationally, and therefore moſt freely. That the difficulties in the <hi>ſtudy of Religion</hi> are ſuch, that true Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mind will diſpoſe, and oblige to a modeſt acquieſcence in the <hi>definition of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That therefore <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> is not a liberty of ſerving God, according to the ſuggeſtions of private fancy without any farther Reſpect, that this is the unhappy fountain of moſt of the <hi>Hereſies, Schiſms,</hi> wild and extravagant <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions</hi> which infeſt and vex the Church.</p>
            <p>That therefore alſo, it is not an exemption from <hi>Laws Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> or reſtraints in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Celebration of Religion, upon ſuch pains as the Church and State ſhall find neceſſary; that if the <hi>Theory</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of Religion were at the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Choice</hi> of every Subject, it would be impoſſible for the Prince to <hi>preſerve</hi> his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That therefore, laſtly, it is not an indifference to all <hi>Religion;</hi> but a <hi>readineſs</hi> of <hi>mind</hi> to embrace whatſoever, either from the nature of the thing, or from the authority with which it comes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93755:21"/>ſhall appear to be True or Good.</p>
            <p>That thus to <hi>ſtudy,</hi> and to <hi>inform</hi> our ſelves, according to our <hi>opportunities,</hi> in the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> of Religion, with due <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, gives a man a <hi>ſteddy Confidence</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> in his Mind, a <hi>ſober judgment,</hi> aſſurance in his Practice. He knows how to <hi>behave</hi> himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the different <hi>modes</hi> and <hi>faſhions</hi> of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Worſhip,</hi> he cannot eaſily be <hi>drawn</hi> into <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> on the one hand, nor into <hi>Schiſm,</hi> by <hi>Scrupuloſity</hi> or <hi>Ignorance</hi> on the other. He eaſily diſtinguiſhes <hi>Graviora Legis</hi> from the <hi>Condientia virtutis,</hi> as <hi>Origen</hi> ſtyles them; finally, the Religion of ſuch a man is his <hi>own,</hi> his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate <hi>act, God</hi> is his <hi>Choice,</hi> and will therefore be his <hi>Reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whoſoever takes the <hi>Meaſures</hi> of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from the conſtitution of <hi>his body,</hi> from vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar opinions of <hi>Sanctity,</hi> from the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of ſuch <hi>particular Perſons</hi> as he ſhall <hi>happen</hi> to <hi>eſteem,</hi> or from any other <hi>Principle</hi> than that of his <hi>own Reaſon</hi> directed <hi>ſoberly</hi> and with all <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> and <hi>deference</hi> to the <hi>Church univerſal,</hi> and that in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93755:21"/>whereof <hi>he</hi> is a <hi>Member</hi> (which is highly and ſtrictly rational) is under the <hi>greateſt ſlavery</hi> that it is poſſible to fall into. For if he be a man of any <hi>underſtanding,</hi> he will always be <hi>perplexed</hi> in his Mind, and diffident in <hi>himſelf,</hi> always <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain,</hi> and therefore always liable to be <hi>troubled</hi> and <hi>confounded,</hi> becauſe the Principles upon which he <hi>proceeds, viz. bodily temper, vulgar opinion, the ſenſe of particular Perſons,</hi> and the like, are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and apt to vary every day.</p>
            <p>And thus, as briefly as I could, I have il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated the <hi>Apoſtles rule,</hi> or the <hi>Wiſdom of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the authority of our Reaſon and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Will from the uſurpations of Prejudice, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Appetites, and Paſſions. I will not be brought under the power of any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What therefore now remains, but that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve <hi>to govern</hi> our Opinions and Practice by this Wiſe and Noble Rule of that <hi>Apoſtle?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How can we conceive a <hi>man</hi> more <hi>perfect</hi> than one whoſe <hi>underſtanding</hi> is free, fitted to judge, and always ready to receive the <hi>Impreſſions</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs:</hi> whoſe Principles are <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:93755:22"/>his Opinion <hi>deliberate,</hi> in Morals <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>upright,</hi> in his Converſation <hi>ſteddy, eaſy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> whoſe Religion is <hi>firm,</hi> and his Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>immoveable?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others may have the <hi>Shape,</hi> theſe only have the <hi>Form,</hi> theſe only live the life of Men. <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherrimum victoriae genus eſt ſeipſum vincere.</hi> It is the moſt <hi>glorious</hi> of <hi>Victories,</hi> the higheſt Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thus to command our ſelves.</p>
            <p>External Acquiſitions may give us power and opportunities of <hi>licentious living,</hi> but <hi>perfect free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> is within our ſelves, when Prejudice and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Pride and Ambition, Envy and Avarice, and all the Legion of contracted Prejudices and Immoveable Habits ſhall be <hi>ſubdued;</hi> when the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God</hi> by the Illuminations of his Spirit, and the Operations of his Grace ſhall make us free, <hi>then ſhall we be free indeed</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17.) To whom with the Father, and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be aſcribed all Honor, Praiſe and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93755:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
